<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Changes Tester Project</title>
    <author email="jruiz@exist.com">Johnny R. Ruiz III</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="0.7.0" date="unconfirmed" description="Entity changes. Feature release with additional bug fixes">
      <action dev="gpampara" type="add">
        Added the revised Entity heirarchy. This effectively allows for dynamic
	properties to be associated with all Entity objects. The main driver
	for the change was the need for extra information with regards to
	coevolution changes that will come into CILib shortly.
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="update">
        Refactored some code and made some methods generic. Cleaned up some
	comments and mainly made sure the tree is currently in a sane state.
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="update">
        Renamed a few methods to make the intention of the methods more clear.
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="update">
        Changed the Type system hierarchy by pushing the isInsideBounds() method
	up into the Type class. This change simplified the DomainParser code.
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="remove">
        Removed the need for a user defined exception class, as the 
	description is the main	need and not the new class.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.6.6" date="2007-03-18" description="Feature release and bug fixes">
      <action dev="gpampara" type="add">
        Added support to define functions within the XML specification file or
	programatically, having the Expression Tree then created and evaluated.
	ExpressionFunction defines this functionality and relies on the
	library JEP (http://jep.sourceforge.net)
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="add">
        Added the new operator system for algorithms using Entities. Main 
	benefactor at the moment is the EC framework.
      </action>
      <action dev="apengelbrecht" type="add">
        Added support to have all ContinuousFunction classes have the ability
	to define relative X-axis and Y-axis shifts. Functions are no longer
	only defined to have their reference point at the origin.
      </action>
      <action dev="gpampara" type="update">
        Added the new changes page to the Maven build prcess to keep track of 
	the changes made within CILib. Also updated some documentation.
      </action>
    </release>
 
<!--    <release version="1.1" date="2005-03-01" description="Subsequent release">
      <action dev="jruiz" type="add">
        Added additional documentation on how to configure the plugin.
      </action>
      <action dev="aramirez" type="fix" issue="MPJIRA-11">
        Enable retrieving component-specific issues.
      </action>
      <action dev="jruiz" type="remove" due-to="Allan Ramirez" due-to-email="aramirez@exist.com">
        The element type " link " must be terminated by the matching end-tag.
        Deleted the erroneous code.
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="1.0" date="2005-01-01" description="First release">
      <action dev="jruiz" type="update">
        Uploaded documentation on how to use the plugin.
      </action>
    </release>-->
  </body>
</document>
