<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright (C) 2003 - 2009
    Computational Intelligence Research Group (CIRG@UP)
    Department of Computer Science
    University of Pretoria
    South Africa

    This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify
    it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
    the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or
    (at your option) any later version.

    This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
    GNU General Public License for more details.

    You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
    along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
    Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA

-->
<document>
  <body>
    <p>
      What follows is a general discussion on the normal workflow for
      CIlib. the usage of the tools, however, is a whole topic on it's
      own. We suggest having a look at the following references:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="http://git-scm.com">The official Git website</a></li>
      <li><a href="http://git-scm.com/documentation">Git documentation</a></li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      The tutorials are very good, especially
      <a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/everyday.html">Everyday Git</a>.
      Also have a look at the <a href="http://book.git-scm.com/">Git Community Book</a>.
    </p>
  <section name="Downloading and installing Git">
    <p>
      Get the software :) Depending on whether you are using Linux,
      Mac or Windows, the installation instructions will vary.
    </p>
    <p>
      Please consult your Linux distribution for information on how to
      install Git. Examples:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Debian or Ubuntu: <code>apt-get install git-core git-email</code></li>
      <li>Gentoo: <code>emerge git</code> (useful to have the <code>tcl</code>
      useflag enabled to get <code>gitk</code> installed)</li>
      <li>Fedora: <code>yum install git</code></li>
      <li>FreeBSD: <a
      href="http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/ports/devel/git">git port</a></li>
      <li>Windows: <a href="msysgit download"></a></li>
      <li><a href="http://git-scm.org">Git homepage</a> for source
      downloads.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      If you are on Mac or Windows, have a look at
      <a href="http://github.com/guides/home">The Github Guides</a> for
      more information on how to install the software..
    </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Configure Git">
    <p>
      We need to tell Git who you are exactly:
    </p>
    <source>
git config --global user.name "My Name"
git config --global user.email "myemail@example.com"
    </source>

    <p>
      If you aren't on Unix, or you are not going tuse sendmail as your
      mail trnasfer agent, you will need to configure a connection to
      an SMTP server:
    </p>
    <source>
git config --global sendemail.smtpserver smtp.example.com
    </source>
    <p>
      If the SMTP server needs you perform a login to send email:
    </p>
    <source>
git config --global sendemail.smtpuser "myusername"
git config --global sendemail.smtppass "myPassWord"
    </source>
  </section>

  <section name="Getting the source repository">
    <p>
      You obviously need to get the repository cloned:
    </p>
    <source>
git clone git://github.com/gpampara/cilib.git
    </source>
    <p>
      Bear in mind that you may also use the <code>http</code> transport
      instead of the <code>git</code> transport to get the repository
      cloned - this is quite useful if you are behind a firewall.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Create a local branch">
    <p>
      Branch. It's good for you!
    </p>
    <p>
      Seriously though, creating a local branch allows you to continue
      make changes to the source tree, compare with other branches and
      allows the creation of patches:
    </p>
    <source>
git branch fix_something
    </source>
    <p>
      or
    </p>
    <source>
git checkout -b fix_something master
    </source>
    <p>
      Switching to a branch is just as simple:
    </p>
    <source>
git checkout fix_something
    </source>
  </section>

  <section name="Make changes by hacking away">
    <p>
      Once you are in your local branch, you can go ahead and create
      changes to the code and commit them. Unlike SVN or CVS, the
      commits that are made will be associated with the current branch,
      and not with the upstream branch.
    </p>
    <p>
      It's important to make sure that once you commit, you create a
      detailed description about what the changes involved or resulted
      in. Have a look at <a href="http://www.tpope.net/node/106">this</a>
      to get an idea of what the commit message should include. Please
      note that detailed messages will be expected to get your commits
      applied to the main branch.
    </p>
    <p>
      Git requires a two phase action to commit changes. Firstly you
      will need to add / delete files to get them into the
      <code>index</code>. After which you can commit them:
    </p>
    <source>
git add path/to/file
git rm path/to/file
git commit
    </source>
    <p>
      To rename a file, request Git to do it for you:
    </p>
    <source>
git mv oldfilename newfilename
    </source>
    <p>
      Deleting files from the repository is a similar command:
    </p>
    <source>
git rm &lt;filename&gt;
    </source>
  </section>

  <section name="Preparing the patches">
    <p>
      Now that you have completed the tasks you wanted to complete, you
      might like to submit the changes as a patch so that the rest of
      the community may benefit from your efforts. To send a patch
      requires a few small actions, the most notable being that we need
      to base the patch off the most recent version in the central
      repository. So, switch to the master branch and update it:
    </p>
    <source>
git checkout master
git pull
    </source>
    <p>
      Next, we switch to the local branch and let git apply all our
      local changes on top of the renewed master that we just pulled:
    </p>
    <source>
git checkout fix_something
git rebase master
    </source>
    <p>
      Finally, create the patch. A file with the name derived from he
      commit message will be created:
    </p>
    <source>
git format-patch -M -C master
    </source>
  </section>

  <section name="Submitting the patches">
    <p>
      All patches should be emailed to the CIlib developers mailing
      list, so that they can be discussed and finally agreed upon to be
      included in the master branch.
    </p>
    <p>
      A very good resource on this topic is <a href="http://repo.or.cz/w/git.git?a=blob;f=Documentation/SubmittingPatches;hb=HEAD">this document</a> in the Git
      distribution.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Updating the repository">
    <p>
      While you are busy with your changes, the upstream repository may have
      advanced. You will want to get the upstream changes into your local
      repository.
    </p>
    <p>
      You would switch to the master branch, then pull or fetch and finally
      update your patches to be based on the new upstream repository.
    </p>
    <source>
git checkout master
git pull origin
git checkout current_local_branch
git rebase master
    </source>
    <p>
      The rebase can of course also be applied against the <code>origin</code>.
    </p>
  </section>
  <section name="Additional tips and tricks">
    <p>
      Adding coloring to your terminal is genarally rather useful, you can
      add that with: (or only a few of these)
    </p>
    <source>
git config --global color.branch auto
git config --global color.diff auto
git config --global color.interactive auto
git config --global color.status auto
git config --global color.pager false
    </source>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
